A Finding Aid to the California Art Club Guest Register and Scrapbooks, 1916-1961, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
California Art Club guest register and scrapbooks
1916-1961
Archives of American Art
California Art Club
AAA.caliart
Archival Resource Key
1.5 Linear feet
The California Art Club guest register and scrapbooks measure 1.5 linear feet and date from 1916 to 1961. Included are guest registers spanning 1927 to 1931; a Year Book 1916 of the California Art Club containing images of member artwork and essays; and eleven scrapbooks with clippings, exhibition materials, club bulletins, and place settings.
Arrangement
Due to the small size of this collection, the materials are arranged as one series.
Series 1: California Art Club Guest Register and Scrapbooks, 1916-1961 (Boxes 1-5; 1.5 linear feet)
Biographical / Historical
The largest and most influential Los Angeles art organization during the early 20th century, the California Art Club was organized in 1909 from the Painters' Club. The group holds exhibitions, member talks, and other programs.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The California Art Club guest register and scrapbooks were donated to the Archives of American Art by Henry Ketting Olivier, a past president of the California Art Club, in 1981.
Scope and Contents
The California Art Club guest register and scrapbooks measure 1.5 linear feet and date from 1916 to 1961. Included are guest registers spanning 1927 to 1931; a Year Book 1916 of the California Art Club containing images of member artwork and essays; and eleven scrapbooks with clippings, exhibition materials, club bulletins, and place settings.
The scrapbooks contain local Los Angeles area newspaper clippings and magazine articles on social events, elections, art forums, club bulletins, and club activities in Los Angeles. Also included is art criticism by critics such as Arthur Millier, Alma May Cook, and Elaine St. Maur, as well as artist obituaries; exhibition announcements and invitations; press releases; and cartoons, sketches, and drawings. These scrapbooks record the events around the club and the Los Angeles art scene, as well as the people and artists involved including Aline Barnsdall, Antony Anderson, Evelyna Nunn Miller, Charles Reiffel, Edouard Vysekal, Theodore B. Modra, Boris Deutsch, Millard Sheets, Mabel Alvarez, Carl Oscar Borg, and Emil J. Kosa.
Art -- California -- Los Angeles; Arts organizations -- California; Art criticism -- California -- Los Angeles; Art critics -- California -- Los Angeles; Artists -- California -- Los Angeles; Cartoons (humorous images); Drawings; Scrapbooks; Sketches; Visitors' books; Alvarez, Mabel, 1891-1985; Anderson, Antony; Barnsdall, Aline, 1882-1946; Borg, Carl Oscar, 1879-1947; Cook, Alma Mae; Deutsch, Boris, 1892 or 5-1978; Kosa, Emil Jean, 1903-1968; Miller, Evelyna Nunn; Millier, Arthur, 1893-; Modra, Theodore B., 1873-1930; Reiffel, Charles P., 1862-1942; Sheets, Millard, 1907-1989; St. Maur, Elaine; Vysekal, Edouard A., 1890-1939
- California Art Club Guest Register and Scrapbooks, 1916-1961; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 1.5 Linear feet 5 boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Included here are guest registers spanning 1927 to 1931; a Year Book 1916 of the California Art Club containing images of member artwork and essays; and eleven scrapbooks.
  The scrapbooks contain local Los Angeles area newspaper clippings and magazine articles on social events, elections, art forums, club bulletins, and club activities in Los Angeles. Also included is art criticism by critics such as Arthur Millier, Alma May Cook, and Elaine St. Maur, as well as artist obituaries; exhibition announcements and invitations; press releases; and cartoons, sketches, and drawings. These scrapbooks record the events around the club and the Los Angeles art scene, as well as the people and artists involved including Aline Barnsdall, Antony Anderson, Evelyna Nunn Miller, Charles Reiffel, Edouard Vysekal, Theodore B. Modra, Boris Deutsch, Millard Sheets, Mabel Alvarez, Carl Oscar Borg, and Emil J. Kosa.
  - Guest Register, 1927 September-1931 August; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Year Book 1916 of the California Art Club, Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook 1, 1927-1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1928 August-1929 April; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook 3, 1929 May-1929 December; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 4, 1930 January-1930 November; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook 5, 1930 November-1931 December; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook 6, 1932 January-1935 February; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook 7, 1939 July-1942 March; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 8, 1942 May-1945 May; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2-4)
  - Scrapbook 9, 1945 May-1947 December; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
  - Scrapbook 10, 1948 January-1953 August; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4-8)
  - Scrapbook 11, 1953 September-1961 December; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1-3)